Guide to the Cecily McMillan Papers TAM.807
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Cecily McMillan Papers
1961-2020
2007-2019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
McMillan, Cecily, 1988-
TAM.807
10.63 Linear Feet in 18 manuscript boxes, 1 shared CD box, 1 shared card box, 1 small flat box, 1 oversized flat box, 1 shared oversized flat box, and 4 oversized flat file folders
213.82 Megabytes in 1254 computer files
Cecily McMillan (she/they, born 1988) is an activist and prisoner rights advocate. She was a participant in the Occupy Wall Street momement (OWS), and was arrested and convicted of felony second-degree assault during an incident at an OWS protest in Zuccotti Park on March 17, 2012. McMillan's arrest, trial, sentencing, and subsequent 58 days of incarceration at Rikers Island were highly publicized, and criticized by supporters as a miscarriage of justice highlighting the prevalence of police brutality and the prison industrial complex. Since their release, McMillan has become an ardent prisoner rights advocate, highlighting the connections between poverty and incarceration. The Cecily McMillan Papers (dated 1961-2020, bulk 2007-2019) consist of materials created and collected by McMillan documenting her personal life, education, and activism, with particular emphasis on her participation in the Occupy Wall Street movement and highly publicized arrest, trial, and incarceration. Materials include journals, correspondence, ephemera, meeting notes, photographs, research materials, and publications from Rikers Island. Additionally, there are personal materials such as diplomas, graduation programs, photographs, and correspondence.
Scope and Contents
The Cecily McMillan Papers (dated 1961-2020, bulk 2007-2019) consist of materials created and collected by McMillan documenting her personal life, education, and activism, with particular emphasis on her participation in the Occupy Wall Street movement and highly publicized arrest, trial, and incarceration. McMillan's journals, notes, and collected printed ephemera document their engagement with the Occupy Wall Street (OWS) movement, including meetings and planning sessions. Their arrest, trial, and incarceration at Rikers Island in 2014 is extensively documented in this collection, and includes materials from their trial and sentencing; correspondence with attorneys; correspondence with family, friends, and other individuals expressing solidarity during their incarceration; handbooks and other administrative documents created by the New York City Department of Correction; and notes and journals documenting their daily routine while incarcerated at Rikers. These materials document not only McMillan's experiences and the impact of her incarceration on her wellbeing, employment, and housing situations, but also the administrative and bureaucratic aspects of incarceration, such as how individuals can communicate with others, what they are allowed to be in possession of, and many other aspects of daily life. Materials in this collection also reflect McMillan's broad activism and prisoner rights advocacy through collected zines and printed ephemera. This collection also documents McMillan's early life, education, life after her release, and the impact of her incarceration on her physical and mental wellbeing. These materials include correspondence, photographic prints, and high school and college course materials.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into 3 series, as follows:
Series I. Personal
Series II. Trial and Incarceration
Series III. Activism
All of the series are arranged chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Cecily McMillan in February 2022; the accession number associated with this gift is 2022.018.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Biographical Note
Cecily McMillan (she/they, born 1988) is an activist and prisoner rights advocate. She was a participant in the Occupy Wall Street momement (OWS), and was arrested and convicted of felony second-degree assault during an incident at an OWS protest in Zuccotti Park on March 17, 2012. McMillan's arrest, trial, sentencing, and subsequent 58 days of incarceration at Rikers Island were highly publicized, and criticized by supporters as a miscarriage of justice highlighting the prevalence of police brutality and the prison industrial complex. Since their release, McMillan has become an ardent prisoner rights advocate, highlighting the connections between poverty and incarceration. McMillan's writing has appeared in The New York Times and AlterNet. Their memoir The Emancipation of Cecily McMillan was published by Bold Type Books in 2016, and includes materials from their time as a student activist at The New School in 2011 through their work following their release from prison. As of 2024, McMillan is working for an organization called Queer Equity.
Appraisal
One box of personal effects of the donor's family were appraised out of the collection and returned to the donor in April 2022. However, in order to document McMillan's life outside of her arrest, many of her personal records were retained, including personal photographs, Organization of Staff Analysts hat, high school diploma and commemorative box, college yearbook, sorority sash, recommendation letters, graded assignments, and ticket stubs.
Rikers Island (N.Y.); Protest movements -- United States.; Imprisonment; Prisoners -- Civil rights; Social movements.; Trials.; McMillan, Cecily, 1988-; Occupy Wall Street (Movement); New York (N.Y.). Police Department
- Series I. Personal, 1961-2019; 5.31 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes, 1 small flat box, 1 oversized flat box, and 1 shared oversized flat box; 209.93 Megabytes in 1253 computer files
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of personal and educational materials created and collected by McMillan throughout her life. Many of these materials, especially those related to her college and graduate school courses, illustrate the theories and ideas that influenced and informed their activism. School materials include McMillan's recommendation letters, syllabi, readings, planners, notebooks, class assignments, and meeting minutes for groups in which they participated, such as the Dean's Advisory Council. In addition, there is some personal correspondence, playbills of theater productions in which they were involved, and medical records describing their medical decline post-incarceration. Also included are personal photographs (both physical and digital), a high school diploma and commemorative box, a sorority sash, scrapbooks, and ticket stubs.
  - Family Photographs, 1961-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cecily's Birth Year -- Photographs, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Early Childhood -- Photographs, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Childhood -- Photographs, 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7-9, Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Middle School -- Photographs, Poems, Journal, and Camp Songs, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - High School, 2003-2007
    - Scrapbooks, Photographs, Planners, Journals, and Correspondence, 2003-2007 (Box 2, Folder 9, Box 3, Folder 1-6, Box 4, Folder 1-5, Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Digital Photographs, 2006-2007; TW_TAM_807_ER_1
  - College and Scholarship -- Acceptance, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - High School Graduation -- Diploma, Box, Program, and Correspondence, May 2007 (Box 5, Folder 3, Box 8)
  - Lawrence University, 2007-2011
    - Correspondence, Photograph Prints, Planners, and Assignments, 2007-2011 (Box 5, Folder 4-7, Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Digital Photographs, 2007-2008; TW_TAM_807_ER_2
    - Ride Share Poster and Painting, circa 2008-2011 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - The Lawrentian, February 11, 2011 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Graduation -- Program and Correspondence, June 2011 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The New School, New York City, 2011-2014
    - Correspondence, Photographs, and Assignments, 2011-2013 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - The New School Free Press and The Indypendent, 2013-2014 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Planners, January-March 2014 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Post-Rikers -- New York City and Atlanta, 2014-2017
    - Photographs, circa 2014-2015 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Ticket Stubs, and Planners, 2014-2015 (Box 7, Folder 2, Box 20, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, Planner, and Theater Programs, 2016-2017 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Georgia State University -- PhD Program -- Application, Assignments, Disability Materials, and Planners, 2017-2019 (Box 7, Folder 4-6, Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Health Decline, 2018 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Atlanta -- Correspondence, Notes, Playscript, and Theater Poster, 2018-2019 (Box 9, Folder 3, Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Playscript by Cecily -- "Cigarette Break", undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Series II. Trial and Incarceration, 2012-2018; 2.63 Linear Feet in 6 manuscript boxes and 1 oversized flat file folder
  This series consists of legal documents and materials compiled by McMillan leading up to her trial, during the trial, during her incarceration, and after her release. All of the materials in this series reflect McMillan's experience of knowing, in their own words, "what it's like to lose your freedom, to abandon any sense of personal space, and to face a level of humiliation that is almost impossible to describe". Materials include trial and appeals transcripts; probation terms; McMillan's handwritten notes about their trial; notebooks and journals written during incarceration; correspondence with attorneys, friends, family, supporters, and other incarcerated individuals; Department of Correction's publications and notices; research materials (articles on court support and rights for incarcerated individuals); and press and publicity about McMillan's case. Additionally, there are event schedules, correspondence, and planning documents created by #Justice4Cecily, the campaign created to support and advocate on behalf of McMillan, and transcript of a trial of a deceased fellow incarcerated individual in whose behalf McMillan testified.
  Source Cited
  "I Went From Grad School to Prison," Cosmopolitan, published August 12, 2014, https://www.cosmopolitan.com/politics/a29775/cecily-mcmillan-grad-school-to-jail/
  - Preparing for Trial and #Justice4Cecily, 2012-2014
    - Correspondence, Planners, Zines, and Event Notices, 2012-2014 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
    - Oversize Planning Materials, undated (Flat-file-folder TAM807.1)
  - Trial Transcript, 2014 (Box 10, Folder 1-7, Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Sentencing -- Transcript, Speech, Letters of Support, and Probation Conditions, 2014 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - New York City Department of Correction -- Handbooks, Notices, and Records, 2014 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Prison Notebook(s)", May 5-July 2, 2014 (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
  - #Justice4Cecily -- Cecily's Notes and Correspondence, 2014 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Rikers Letters, 2014 (Box 12, Folder 1-5, Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Talking Points for Release, 2014 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Press, Publicity, and Photographs, 2014 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Welcome Home Letters, 2014 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Probation Conditions and Termination, 2014-2017 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Appeals Case, 2016-2018 (Box 13, Folder 7, Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Estate of Judy Jean Caquias, Deceased, v. City of New York, et al. -- Transcript, 2018 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
- Series III. Activism, 1970-2020; 4.18 Linear Feet in 6 manuscript boxes, 1 oversized flat box, 1 shared oversized flat box, and 3 oversized flat file folders; 3888 kilobytes in 1 document
  This series contains materials related to McMillan's activism and lifelong commitment to civil rights movements. Included are Occupy Wall Street materials (publications including The Occupy Wall Street Journal and Tidal, banners, posters, agendas, zines, flyers, guidelines on "knowing your rights" and nonviolent action, and schedules); agendas, charters, and meeting minutes for various groups (#ResistRikers campaign, Metro Atlanta Democratic Socialists of America, and Bum Rush the Vote/Manny for the People Campaign for State Senate); advocacy materials for other incarcerated individuals (including her brother, James); and publicity and press for the publication of their memoir.
  - McMillan, James, circa 2008-2019
    - Correspondence and Legal Documents, circa 2008-2012 (Box 14, Folder 4-6, Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Juvenile Detention Research, circa 2019 (Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and Advocacy on Behalf of Other Incarcerated Individuals, 2008-2020 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Business Cards, circa 2011-2018 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Occupy Wall Street, 2011-2013
    - Planners, Memos, Correspondence, Event Postcards, and Articles, 2011-2013 (Box 15, Folder 4-5, Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Newspapers, 2011-2012 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Posters and Oversize Planning Sheets, 2011-2013 (Box 20, Folder 3, Flat-file-folder TAM807.2)
    - Banners, undated (Flat-file-folder TAM807.3, Flat-file-folder TAM807.4)
    - "The Philosophy of Occupy Wall Street", April 12, 2014; TW_TAM_807_ER_3
  - Metro Atlanta Democratic Socialists of America, 2011-2019 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
  - Bum Rush the Vote, 2012 (Box 16, Folder 5, Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Organization of Staff Analysts, May 2013-January 2014 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - "The Cadre" -- Nonviolence and Direct Action Trainings, September 2013-December 2014 (Box 16, Folder 7, Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Bayard Rustin and "Building a Movement Today" -- Research Materials, Drafts, and Notes, circa 2013-2017 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - #Resist Rikers, 2014-2017 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Activism Efforts -- General, 2014-2020 (Box 17, Folder 4, Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Tribute to Harlon's 2000th Program and WRFG Birthday Celebration -- Planning Committee, 2016 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Memoir -- Notes, Research Materials, and Publicity, 2016-2017 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Lectures and Symposia, 2016-2018 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Book Consulting Projects, 2018-2019 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Zines, 1970-1976 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Zines, circa 1985-2002 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Zines, 2005-2006 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Zines, circa 2006-2014 (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
  - Zines, 2007-2008 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Zines, 2009 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Zines, 2010 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Zines, 2011 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Zines, 2012 (Box 18, Folder 11, Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Zines, circa 2012-2014 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Zines, 2013 (Box 19, Folder 3-4)
  - Zines, 2014 (Box 19, Folder 5-6)
  - Zines, 2015-2018 (Box 19, Folder 7)